［ワキ］是は都北山紫野
([WAKI] I am a priest living at Urin-in in Murasakino,)
雲林院に住居する僧にて候。
(in the Northern hills of the capital.)
さても我一夏の間花を立て候。
(I have offered flowers throughout the summer.)
早安居も過方になり候へば
(As my period of retreat is coming to a close,)
色よき花を集め。
(I will gather fine blossoms)
花の供養を取り行はゞやと存じ候。
(and perform a memorial service for the flowers.)
［ワキ］敬つて白す立花供養の事。
([WAKI] With reverence, I proclaim this memorial service for flowers.)
右非情草木たりといへども。
(Though they are said to be insentient plants,)
此花広林に開けたり。
(these flowers blossom in wide woodlands.)
豈心なしといはんや。
(How could they be said to be without feelings?)
中んづく泥を出でし蓮。
(Especially the lotus appearing from the mud)
一乗妙典の題目たり。
(and that has become the title of the one sublime law.)
此結縁に引かれ。
(Drawn by this time even plants, trees,)
草木国土悉皆成仏道。
(all the earth, achieve Buddhahood.)
［シテ］手に取れば
([SHITE] As when the hand takes them,)
たぶさに穢る立てながら
(the hand itself sullies them.)
三世の仏に
(To the Buddhas of the Three Realms)
花奉る。
(I offer them as they are.)
［ワキ］不思議やな今までは
([WAKI] How strange! Until now)
草花りよようとして見えつる中に
(I saw them only as flowers grasses, yet among them)
白き花のおのれ独り笑の眉を
(I see a single white flower whose brows seem)
開けたるは
(to unfold in a smile)
如何なる花を立てけるぞ。
(What manner of flower are you offering ?)
［シテ］愚の御僧の仰せやな
([SHITE] A foolish question, holy priest.)
黄昏時の折なるに
(Though in this twilight hour you see it,)
などかはそれと御覧ぜざる。さりながら
(You do not recognize this flower!)
名は人めきて賤しき垣ほにかゝりたれば
(Its name seeming human, on lowly hedges it hangs,)
知ろしめさぬは理なり。
(that you do not know its name is reasonable.)
是は夕顔の花にて候
(This is the 'evening face' flower.)
［ワキ］実に〳〵さぞと夕顔の
([WAKI] Indeed, it is an "evening face"!)
花の主は如何なる人ぞ。
(Who is it that has offered this flower?)
［シテ］名のらずと終には知ろし召さるべし。
([SHITE] Without giving my name you will know it in the end.)
我は此花の陰より参りたり。
(I have come from this flower's shadow.)
［ワキ］さては此世になき人の。
([WAKI] So then, are you no longer in the world)
花の供養に逢はん為めか。
(and came to attend this memorial service for flowers?)
それに付けても名のり給へ。
(But please, you must tell me your name.)
［シテ］名は有りながら亡き跡に。
([SHITE] I have a name, though I am no longer alive,)
なりし昔の物語。
(part of an old story.)
［ワキ］何某の院にも。
([WAKI] At a certain mansion,)
［シテ］常はさむらふ誠には。
([SHITE] I could always be found, indeed it is so.)
［地謡］五条あたりと夕顔の。
([JIUTAI] Near Gojō, she said, of the "evening face.")
五条あたりと夕顔の。
(Near Gojō, she said, of the "evening face.")
空目せし間に夢となり。
(In the moment the eyes turn aside, she becomes a dream.)
面影ばかり亡き跡の
(Only her image lingers behind)
立花の陰に隠れけり。
(as she disapperas in the shadow of the flowers.)
(She disappears in the shadow of the flowers.)
（狂言）かように候う者は、
([KYŌGEN] I am someone who lives)
都北山あたりに、住まいする者にて候、
(in the Kitayama area of the capital.)
承り候えば、
(I have heard that near here,)
あたり近き、雲林院において、一夏の間、
(at Unrin-in, there will be memorial services)
花の供養の御座候よし、
(for the lowers offered over the summer.)
承りおよびて候ほどに我らも、参らばやと存ずる、
(This being the case, I too, intend to go there.)
まことに、今日った参る人も少なく、
(Truly, as few people are going there this evening,)
何とやらん、ものさびて候よ、
(it is rather melancholy.)
（ワキ）のうのう方々はこの辺りの人にて候か、
([WAKI ]Ho, there! Are you someone from around here ?)
（狂言）なかなかこの辺りの者にて候、
([KYŌGEN]  Indeed, I am a person from this area.)
（ワキ）左様に候わば、まず近こう御入り候え、ものを
([WAKI] If that's the case, first of all, could you come closer ?)
尋ねたきことの候、
(There is something I would like to ask you.)
（狂言）心得申して候
([KYŌGEN] Certainly.)
さて、御尋ねなされたきとは、
(Well then, what is the matter)
如何様なる、御用にて候ぞ、
(you would like to ask me about ?)
（ワキ）思し召しよらざる申し事にて候えども
([WAKI] While it isn't a circumstance of much importance,)
古しえ、五条辺りに、夕顔の上の住ませ給いし仔細、
(I would like you to tell me the particulars of the story of Lady Yūgao,)
御物語候え、
(of the Evening Faces, who lived here long ago.)
（狂言）これは思いも寄らぬ事を、御尋ねなされ候ものかな、
([KYŌGEN] This is an unexpected request you've made of me.)
我等も左様の事詳しくは存ぜず候が、およそ、
(I don't know about the situation in much detail, but)
承りたる通り、物語申そうずるにて候、
(I will do the best I can to tell you the story as I have heard it.)
さる程に、夕顔の上と申したる、御方は、
(Well then, the one known as Lady Yūgao was the daughter)
三位の中将の、御息女にて、
(of a middle captain of the third rank, and,)
さる仔細の事候いて、
(owing the certain circumstances,)
五条辺りに忍び居て御座ありたると申す、
(she came to live in seclusion in the area of Gojo.)
またその頃、光源氏は、
(Also at the at time, Hikaru Genji)
六条御息所の方へ御通いなされ候が、
(was paying regular visit to the home of Lady Rokujo.)
折節五条辺りを、通られしかば、
(On occasion he would pass through the Gojo area)
しょうやに夕顔の花、
(and it happened that there was a simple dwelling there)
見事に咲き乱れ候程に、
(with "evening faces" blooming in splendid profusion.)
惟光をめされ、あの花、
(He called Koremitsu to him,)
手折りてまいれとの御事なり、
(and requested that he go pluck a blossom.)
惟光御随身をもって、その花を所望申されしかば、
(When Koremitsu spoke to his attendant,)
しょうやより童を出だし、
(a child came out of the house, and,)
しばらくそれに、御待ちあれとて、
(having asked that he wait there for a wile, soon after,)
その後、白き扇の、つまいと焦がしたるに、
(offered him a white fan, its edges perfumed with incense,)
夕顔の花をそえて指し出だす、
(on which rested a blossom of the "evening faces".)
御随身これを受け取り、惟光に参らせければ、
(The attendant took this and returned with it to Koremitsu.)
惟光、源氏へ参らせ候ところに、
(Koremistu went with it to Genji, who,)
その扇の縁に、一首の歌の御座候ほどに、
(seeing then that there was a poem on the edge of the fan,)
急ぎ御返歌をなされ、
(quickly wrote a verse in reply.)
その花ゆえに、夕顔の上に見え給い、
(Because of that flower, he was drawn to the Lady Yūgao,)
御契り浅からねば、その後、
(of the evening faces, and as the vows they shared were not shallow,)
何某院へ御伴いなされ、
(after that he came to stay together with her there at her dwelling.)
色々比翼連理の契り
(Even as the purity of the many pledges)
浅からず候ところに、
(they exchanged were profound-)
なんぼう、不思議なる事にて候、
(By the Sacred Treaures! Mysteroiusly,)
夕顔の上は、物怪に犯され給ひ、
(Lady Yūgao was possessed)
空しくなられたると申す、
(by some sort of vengeful spirit, and it is said that all was lost...)
光源氏の御嘆き申すも、
(As to Hikaru Genji's grief, its depth was limitless)
愚かなる体にて御座ありたると申す、
(as there was nothing to be done for her, it is said.)
まず、我らの承りたる仔細、
(In any event, those are the details,)
大方かくのごとくにて候が、
(at least in broad terms, as I know them.)
只今はなにと、思し召してやらん、
(But why are you interested in this)
御尋ね不審に存じ候、
(and asking me about this matter now ? I find it suspicious.)
（ワキ）懇ろに承り候ものかな、
([WAKI] I'm grateful that you have described the matter so thoroughly.)
それがし一夏の間、花の供養を
(When I was performing a memorial service for flowers)
執り行い候ところに、
(offered during the summer, a woman appeared)
女性一人白き花をたてられ候ほどに、
(and gave me a white flower.)
花の主はいかなる人ぞと
(I asked who, and what sort of person, she was with the flower,)
尋ねて候えば、それにつき
(to which she replied speaking of the Lady of the Evening Faces)
夕顔の上の御事を我が身の上の様に言い捨て、
(as though she spoke of herself.)
そのまま花の陰にて姿を
(Then she disappeared in the shadow of the flowers.)
見失いて候よ
(That's what happened.)
（狂言）言語道断、不思議なる事を
([KYŌGEN] How astonishing!)
仰せ候ものかな、
(What a wondrous thing you have related to me.)
さては我らが推量申すに、
(Now then, if I may say what I suppose, it can only be that)
斯様に花の供養の御座候間、
(when you were performing the memorial service for flowers,)
夕顔の花の精、または古え夕顔の上ご亡心、
(the spirit of the "yugao flower", and also the ghost of Lady Yūgao,)
現れ出たると存じ候がしかとは存ぜず候、
(Lady of the Evening Faces, of long ago appeared before you.)
去りながら、お僧尊くましますにより
(This being the case, I believe that due to)
御弔いにも預かりたく思し召し、
(the merit emanating from your Reverence,)
夕顔の上のご亡心
(the spirit of the Lady Yūgao appeared to you in order)
現れ出たると存じ候、
(to ask that you offer prayers for her deliverance.)
左様に候はばこれより五条辺りへ御出で候はば、
(If that is the case, you should go now to the Gojo area,)
奇特なることも御座候ほどに、
(where a miracle will surely occur. Then you should pray earnestly)
そののち懇ろに弔うて御通りあれかしと存じ候、
(for her enlightenment as she has requested of you.)
（ワキ）我らも左様に存じ候間、
([WAKI] As I also believe this to be true,)
五条辺りに立ち出で、
(I will go to the Gojo area and pray there)
夕顔の上の御跡を弔い申そうずるにて候、
(For the ghost of the Lady Yūgao and her deliverance.)
（狂言）それは近頃にて候、お僧御出にて候はば
([KYŌGEN] As you will be going there shortly,)
我らも御後より参ろうずるにて候、
(I'll follow after your Recerence in a while.)
（ワキ）やがて後より来られ候え、
([WAKI] In due time then, I will expect you there.)
（狂言）心得申して候、
([KYŌGEN] I'll do as you say.)
［ワキ］有りし教へに随つて
([WAKI] Following what I was told earlier)
五条あたりに来て見れば
(I have to go to Gojo to see:)
実にも昔の居まし所
(Indeed, the mansion, as in the past,)
さながら宿りも夕顔の
(the dwelling and its evening faces.)
瓢簞しば〳〵空し
(Gourds now often empty,)
草顔淵が巷に滋し。
(and (Genken's) Yen Yūan's home overgrown with weeds.)
［シテ］藜藋深く鎖せり。
([SHITE] Densely closed off by goosefoot,)
夕陽の残晴新に
(the evening sun creates mountain shadows,)
窓を穿つて去る。
(comes through the window and then leaves.)
［地謡］愁嘆の泉の声。
([JIUTAI] The faint sound of a hidden spring.)
雨原憲が枢を湿ほす。
(Rain dampens Genken's (Yüan Hsien) gate.)
［シテ］さらでも袖を湿ほすは
([SHITE] But what dampens the sleeves is)
廬山の雪の曙。
(dawn on the snow on Mount Lu.)
［地謡］窓頭に向ふ朗月は。
([JIUTAI] Through the east window the limpid moon,)
窓頭に向ふ朗月は。
(Through the east window the limpid moon,)
琴瑟に当り
(on the zither stand casts its light.)
愁傷の秋の山。
(Beyond the hedge, the autumn mountains.)
物すごの気色や。
(Such a desolate evening!)
［地謡］実に物すごき風の音。
([JIUTAI] Indeed, the desolate sound of the wind,)
簀戸の竹垣有りし世の。
(the wicker bamboo fence as in the past.)
夢の姿を見せ給へ。
(Please show me your form in a dream)
菩提を深く弔らはん。
(I will pray in earnest for your soul.)
［シテ］山の端の。心も知らで行く月は
([SHITE] The moon, uncertain of the mountain ridge as it went)
上の空にて絶えし跡の。
(and disappeared in the sky high above without a trace.)
又いつか逢ふべき。
(When will they meet again ?)
［地謡］山賤の。垣ほ荒るとき折々は
([JIUTAI] Though the mountain dweller's fence has fallen into ruin, from time to time)
［シテ］哀をかけよ撫子の。
([SHITE] Show compassion for the wild pink)
［地謡］花の姿をまみえなば。
([JIUTAI] Blossom, if I reaveal the form)
［シテ］跡訪ふべきか。
([SHITE] Will you pray for my soul ?)
［地謡］中々に。
([JIUTAI] Certainly, I will.)
［シテ］さらばと思ひ夕顔の。
([SHITE] Thinking, "well then,"  the "evening face")
［地謡］草の半蔀おし上げて。
([JIUTAI] The vine-covered lattice shutter pushes open,)
立ち出づる御姿。
(revealing her form as she steps out.)
見るに涙のとゞまらず。
(At the sight tears flow without stopping.)
［地謡］其頃源氏の。
([JIUTAI] At that time, Genji)
中将と聞こえしは
(the Middle Captain as he was called,)
此夕顔の草枕。
(shared the grass pillow of this "evenig face" for a brief rest.)
たゞ仮臥の夜もすがら
(Through the night they heard from next door)
隣を聞けば三吉野や。
(a pilgrim's voice in prayer)
御嶽精進の御声にて。
(about ascending the sacred peak at Miyoshino.)
南無当来導師。弥勒仏とぞ称へける。
("Save us, holy guide of the way in the future, Maitreya Buddha!", he chanted.)
今も尊き御供養に。其時の思ひ
(Even now this service has brought back the memory)
出でられて。そゞろに濡るゝ袂かな。
(of that time and unmittingly tears dampen my sleeves.)
猶それよりも忘れぬは
(But more than that, I cannot forget the evening)
源氏此宿を。見そめ給ひし夕つ方。
(when Genji first saw this house.)
惟光を招き寄せ。
(Beckoning to Koremitsu,)
あの花折れと宣へば。
("Pick that flower for me," he ordered.)
白き扇の。つまいたう焦がしたりしに。
(On a white fan, its edges perfumed with incense,)
此花を折りて参らする。
(the flower was picked and presented.)
［シテ］源氏つくづくと御覧じて。
([SHITE] Genji, gazing at it intently,)
［地謡］打ち渡す 遠方人に問ふとても。
([JIUTAI] "Of you passing in the distance..." he asked)
それ其花と答へずは。
(and if I had not answered about the flower)
終に知らでもあるべきに。逢ひに扇を手に触るゝ。
(forever we must have remained strangers. We were brought together)
契の程のうれしさ。
(by the fan touched by our hands, in a joyous pledge of love.)
折々尋ね寄るならば。
(If from time to time)
定めぬ海士の此宿の。
(I visit this dwelling of a homeless fishergirl)
主を誰と白波の。
(not knowing the owner's name, I hope)
よるべの末を頼まんと
(to be as white foam finding at last the shore, he thought,)
一首を詠じおはします。
(and composed a poem.)
［地謡］折りてこそ。
([JIUTAI] If you pick it)
［シテ］折りてこそ
([SHITE] If you pick it)
それかとも見め
(then, indeed you will know it)
黄昏に。
(in the twilight)
［地謡］ほのぼの見えし
([JIUTAI] Faintly visible:)
花の夕顔。
(The flowering "evening face",)
(the flowering "evening face",)
花の夕顔。
(the flowering "evening face".)
［シテ］終の宿りは知らせ申しつ。
([SHITE] "As my final home I have shown you)
［地謡］常にはとむらひ。
([JIUTAI] Always pray for me)
［シテ］おはしませと。
([SHITE] I beg you", she said, and)
［地謡］木綿附の鳥の音。
([JIUTAI] as she spoke the crowing of the cocks,)
［シテ］鐘もしきりに。
([SHITE] The tolling of the bells too,)
告げ渡る東雲。
(announce the coming of dawn.)
［地謡］あさまにもなりぬべし。
([JIUTAI] As nothing will be hidden in the morning light,)
明けぬ先にと夕顔の宿り。
("Before dawn breaks, to the dwelling of the "evening face",)
明けぬ先にと夕顔の宿りの。
("before dawn breaks, to the dwelling of the "evening face",)
又半蔀の内に入りて
(she says, and again goes within the lattice shutter,)
其まま夢とぞなりにける。
(just so, becoming one with the dream.)